General Information

General Information

Admission Categories

Assured Admission. First-time students who graduate from an accredited high school, have successfully demonstrated competency in the required five subject areas, and meet minimum performance requirements are assured admission to the University. These five subject areas are English, mathematics, natural sciences, social studies, and foreign language. Successful completion of a minimum of 16 core course requirements, either at the secondary school level or at the college level, is typically used to demonstrate competency. Performance requirements for freshmen include an ACT composite score of 20 or higher, or an SAT combined score of 950 or higher, or a high school class rank in the upper one-half of the graduating class.

Prospective transfer students are also expected to demonstrate competency in the core course requirements, as well as have a cumulative grade point average of at least a C average (2.0 on a 4.0 scale) and at least a C average in the last semester of college enrollment. Several UNL undergraduate colleges require higher grade point averages for transferring into specific academic programs. See the college sections in this bulletin for more specific information about transfer requirements.

Removal of Deficiencies. Because admission requirements establish the level of knowledge and skills which are needed for a student to succeed at UNL, students who are admitted with core course deficiencies are expected to quickly remove them. Although students are encouraged to remove all admission deficiencies prior to enrolling at UNL by taking course work in high school, by correspondence, or in a community college, students who choose to remove their admission deficiencies at UNL will be required to enroll immediately in the specified courses needed to remove their deficiencies and to remain enrolled in such courses each term until their deficiencies are fully removed.

Students must remove admission deficiencies within the following time periods:

4th year math admission deficiency–no later than either 1) the semester in which the student has attempted his or her first 30 credit hours at UNL, or 2) if longer, one calendar year from the time the student first enrolled at UNL.
any foreign language admission deficiency–no later than either 1) the semester in which the student has attempted his or her first 60 credit hours at any campus in the university system, or 2) if longer, two calendar years from the time the student first enrolls at any campus in the university system.
all other admission deficiencies–no later than either 1) the semester in which the student has attempted his or her first 30 credit hours at any campus in the university system or 2) if longer, one calendar year from the time the student first enrolled at any campus in the university system.

These time periods represent the maximum period for removing admission deficiencies. Shorter periods may apply in individual situations depending upon a variety of factors considered in the admission review process (e.g., the expected graduation date, the program in which the student wishes to enroll, the sequence of courses required to remove the admission deficiency).

Students who fail to successfully compensate for their admission deficiencies within the established time will not be allowed to continue their enrollment at UNL until they have removed all their deficiencies.

College-level course work taken to remove high school core course requirements will not count toward graduation requirements in most of the undergraduate colleges at UNL. It will be used as elective credit only in some of the undergraduate colleges. The College of Business Administration and the College of Architecture will not count these courses towards meeting graduation requirements, not even as elective credit. The College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources and the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts will consider courses taken to remove deficiencies to satisfy graduation requirements. The College of Education and Human Sciences course work taken to remove high school deficiencies policy is available in the College Academic Advising Center, 105 Henzlik. Additional information about University policies governing the removal of admissions deficiencies is available from the student’s academic adviser.

Undergraduate Transfer Credit Policy

This statement outlines important information for students who present undergraduate credit for transfer to a degree program at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. Transfer credit is any post-secondary credit earned at an institution outside the University of Nebraska–Lincoln, including other institutions in the University of Nebraska System (NCTA, UNK, UNO, and UNMC).

The college within the University of Nebraska–Lincoln in which a student enrolls (the degree college) has ultimate responsibility for determining how all credit, including transfer credit, will apply to a specific degree program. Evaluation of transfer credit is based on a review of the comparability of the nature, content and level of the learning experience and its appropriateness to the student’s degree program. The acceptance and use of transfer credit are subject to limitations in accordance with the educational policies of The University of Nebraska–Lincoln.

Transfer Credit Practices

The University of Nebraska–Lincoln endorses the Joint Statement on Transfer and Award of Academic Credit approved by the American Council on Education (ACE), the American Association of Collegiate Registrars and Admissions Officers (AACRAO), and the Council for Higher Education Accreditation (CHEA). The current issue of Transfer Credit Practices of Designated Educational Institutions, published by AACRAO is an example of a reference used in determining transfer credit.

Applicants must request an official transcript sent to the Office of Admissions from each college attended. Failure to provide transcripts from all colleges or universities attended may result in denial of the application or dismissal from the university. Grades from institutions outside the Universities in the NU System will be used for evaluation and admission, but will not become part of the University cumulative Grade Point Average (GPA). Each degree college determines its policy for acceptance and application of grades below C to degree requirements.

A. Credit presented for transfer from within the University of Nebraska System

Credit earned at any institution within the University of Nebraska System will be accepted by UNL. Applicability to degree requirements is determined by the student’s degree college. Direct course equivalencies with UNK, UNO and

UNMC, established by faculty, are maintained by the NU System and are available on-line at http://coursefinder.nebraska.edu. Applicability of courses without direct equivalencies will be at the discretion of the degree college.

B. Inter-institutional Agreements

Associate to Baccalaureate Agreements. Agreements have been established for specific programs at selected community colleges.

Transfer courses equivalencies. Direct equivalencies have been established by UNL faculty for courses from a number of institutions including Nebraska Community Colleges and Nebraska College of Technical Agriculture. Applicability of courses without direct equivalencies will be at the discretion of the degree college. Transfer Course Equivalency tables are available on-line at http://admissions.unl.edu/tequiv/index.php. While every effort is made to ensure accuracy, this information is subject to change.

C. Credit presented for transfer which requires additional review by the degree college.

The following types of transfer credit require additional review by the student’s degree college within UNL to determine applicability to the student’s program of study.

Credit in courses presented for transfer which do not have a direct equivalent as established by UNL faculty.
Credit in courses determined by University of Nebraska–Lincoln to be of a developmental, vocational, or technical nature.
Credit in courses or programs in which the institution granting the credit is not directly involved.
Credit presented for transfer from institutions not accredited by one of the regional accrediting commissions. (www.chea.org)
In determining the acceptability of transfer credit from colleges which are not regionally accredited, acceptance practices indicated in the current issue of Transfer Credit Practices of Designated Educational Institutions, an AACRAO publication, will be used as a guide. For institutions not listed in the publication, guidance is requested from the designated reporting institution of the appropriate state.
Credit presented for transfer from institutions outside the United States. Transfer credit from foreign educational institutions may be granted after a determination of the type of institution involved, its recognition by the educational authorities of the foreign country, and an evaluation of the content, level, and comparability of the study to courses and programs at University of Nebraska–Lincoln. Credit may be granted in specific courses or assigned to general areas of study. Questions about foreign credentials and educational systems should be directed to the Office of Admissions.

Special Situations, Qualifications and Limitations related to Transfer of Credit

Applicability of transfer credit to degree requirements

The student’s degree college within the University of Nebraska–Lincoln has ultimate responsibility for determining how all credit, including transfer credit, will apply to a specific degree program.

Transfer credit from two-year institutions

No more than 66 semester or 98 quarter credits earned at two-year colleges can be applied to an undergraduate degree from University of Nebraska–Lincoln.

Lower division credit

Lower division courses transferred to UNL will generally be used to meet lower division requirements. In the event that a lower division transfer course is used as a substitution for an upper division requirement at the university a student may be required to complete additional upper division hours for graduation.

Residency requirement

The University’s colleges may require that specific courses or a certain number of credit hours be completed on the UNL campus to satisfy the residency requirement.

Dual Credit earned while a student is enrolled in high school

When a student earns both high school and college credit for a course, the student must present a transcript from the original postsecondary institution offering credit for the course. Such courses will be evaluated as transfer credit.

Other credit earned while in high school

Many students enroll in one or more college courses while enrolled in high school. An official transcript of all courses attempted must be presented upon application unless the credit was earned at UNL. Credit from institutions outside the University of Nebraska–Lincoln will be evaluated as transfer credit

Credit earned in the US Armed Forces

Students with military service will be awarded 1 credit of military science for every three months of active duty up to a total of four credits. Credit for technical or specialized schools will be accepted to the extent that the material is applicable toward degree requirements at UNL.

Credit by Examination (CBE)

Programs accepted at University of Nebraska–Lincoln include the Advanced Placement (AP) Program, the International Baccalaureate (IB) Examinations, the College Level Examination Program (CLEP), and departmental examinations. For information on specific exams and required scores accepted for credit at UNL see: http://admissions.unl.edu/advanced/#. Credit by Exam (AP, IB, or CLEP credit) may not be transferred directly to University of Nebraska–Lincoln from another institution. However, the scores from these examinations may be sent to University of Nebraska–Lincoln from the testing agency, and credit will be awarded based on UNL’s AP, IB, and CLEP policies.

Students who anticipate applying to professional programs should inquire about the acceptability of Credit by Exam before registering for exams.

Credit by Departmental Examination

Credit by departmental examination allows regularly enrolled students to gain academic credit for knowledge they have acquired by self-study or experience. The student’s knowledge base is expected to parallel that of the specific UNL course for which the student wishes to gain credit. A fee of one-half of resident tuition is charged to administer and/or evaluate an examination for credit. Examinations for credit through UNL departments may be taken only by currently enrolled students. A student is not permitted to receive Credit by Examination in a course which is a prerequisite for a course already taken. Credit earned by examination is not applicable for use in an advanced degree program. Credit granted by another college for placement exams or locally designed test-out examinations will not be accepted in transfer.

University of Nebraska–Lincoln students who earn credit at another institution

Current UNL students are urged to consult with the appropriate academic adviser before enrolling in any course intended to be applied to the student’s degree. Non-UNL credit for Study Abroad programs will be evaluated as transfer credit upon receipt of official transcripts. Current UNL students who wish to enroll in a course at another institution in the NU System should file an Intercampus Application. http://admissions.unl.edu/apply/intercampus.asp

University of Nebraska–Lincoln students who wish to transfer from one UNL college to another

Current UNL students seeking to gain admission to another degree college must meet all standards for admission to the new college as a transfer applicant. The new college will evaluate all of the student’s credit, including transfer credit, to determine which credit will be applicable to degree requirements.

Academic Policies and Procedures

Academic Adviser Assignment

The University considers faculty contact with students essential to academic planning and University life. Undergraduate students are assigned academic advisers through the college or department in which they are majoring. Undergraduate students who have not yet decided upon a college will be referred to an academic adviser in the Division of General Studies.

Students Responsibilities in Academic Advising

The University of Nebraska–Lincoln is committed to providing effective academic advising to students as an essential component of their educational experience.

Department and college advisers are assigned to students in their programs for assistance in assessing educational goals, planning programs of study, understanding program requirements, and following policies and procedures. Professional academic advisers in the Division of General Studies provide these services to students who have not yet declared their undergraduate college or major.

Students are ultimately responsible for fulfilling all the requirements of the curriculum in which they are enrolled. Students are also responsible for initiating advising contacts and preparing for advising sessions. The mentoring relationship between academic advisers and students is confidential and is strengthened by advisers listening with understanding to student concerns.

Students are expected to take responsibility for a successful university experience and effective advising session by:

1. Participating in New Student Enrollment and priority registration programs;

2. Scheduling appointments with advisers well in advance of priority registration and at other times as needed;

3. Identifying class choices from requirements of the selected program or major;

4. Identifying questions to address in advising sessions;

5. Informing advisers of any special needs, deficiencies or barriers that might affect academic success;

6. Following academic policies and procedures and meeting academic calendar deadlines (e.g. registration, fee payment, senior check/degree audit, filing for degree, etc.);

7. Knowing and completing degree or program requirements;

8. Monitoring their progress toward meeting degree requirements by maintaining a copy of their academic records and seeking assistance to resolve any errors or questions; and

9. Acting on recommendations to seek assistance from the various student support services provided by the University.

Insert Registration and Records link on main page

Maximum Credit Hour Load

Undergraduate students may register for up to 18 credit hours per semester, except for the College of Business Administration which allows a maximum of 19 credit hours and the College of Arts and Sciences and the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts which allow a student to register for up to 20 credit hours. Written permission from the college dean is required to exceed the credit hour per semester maximum and must be filed with an Override Authorization Form at the time of registration.

Class Attendance

Students are expected to attend all lectures, recitations, quizzes, and laboratories regularly. The University has no regulation which permits cutting classes.

Students are responsible for the attendance policy set by instructors and should clear absences directly with them.

In cases where a student is unable to contact his or her instructors due to major illness, serious injury, or hospitalization or when given military orders which are effective immediately, a notice may be sent to the student’s instructors by the University Health Center, a family physician, or the Students Affairs Office, 106 Canfield Administration Building, 472-3755. This notice is for the instructor’s information only and does not relieve the student of contacting instructors as soon as possible.

Students involved in University-sponsored activities, including intercollegiate athletics, may need to be excused from a class, lab, or studio meeting. In all instances it is the student’s responsibility to request permission for the absence (preferably in writing) from the instructor and to discuss how the absence will affect their ability to meet the course requirements. Students should do this as soon in the semester as possible. While instructors should seek to the greatest extent possible, consistent with course requirements, to make reasonable accommodation for a student involved in University-sponsored activities, students should recognize that not every course can accommodate absences and neither the absence (nor the notification of an absence) relieves them from meeting the course requirements.

For complete information on class attendance, see the Schedule of Classes.

Courses of Instruction

Subject Area Abbreviations

The University of Nebraska–Lincoln uses standard abbreviations for academic subject areas and program titles as part of course descriptions. This list can be found by clicking on Course Abbreviations under the Courses tab in the heading.

Abbreviations and Symbols Commonly Used In The Bulletin:

ACE Achievement-Centered Education

anly or anlys analysis

appl or apps or ap application or applied

arr arranged

corec corequisite (see parallel)

coreg coregistration (denotes taking another class along with the one listed) (See parallel)

cr or crs credit or credit hours

cr arr credit hours arranged

cum cumulative grade point average (see GPA)

D Extended Education (contract course)

Ed or Educ Education

ES Essential Studies Program

elem elementary

F Distance Education-“Field” Class

fld field

fund or fun fundamentals

G graduate

GPA Grade Point Average

grad or Grad graduate

H Honors

hr or hrs hours

I or inc incomplete

ind independent

intermed intermediate

intro or intr introduction

IS Integrative Studies Program

L laboratory with credit hours

Lab or lab laboratory

Lec lecture

max maximum

NP or N No Pass credit allowed toward degree

NR No Report

P Pass

P/N Pass/No Pass

PO Pass/No Pass grading option

parallel denotes taking another class along with the one listed (a corequisite or coregistration)

Prereq or preq prerequisite

princ principles

Pro or prof professional

PSI Personal System of Instruction

quz quiz

Rec Recreation

rct or Reci recitation

rsh research

S (denotes) Distance Education class

sec secondary

sem semester

smnr seminar

Stu or stu studio

TBA to be assigned

tch teach

tchr teacher

tchng teaching

tech technology or technical

UG undergraduate

UNL University of Nebraska–Lincoln

UNMC University of Nebraska Medical Center

UNO University of Nebraska at Omaha

W withdrew

X College Independent Study course

/ and/or

& and

+ and

> greater than

< less than

- dash or “to”

Course Prerequisites and Corequisites

Course prerequisites indicate the level of preparation a student must have had to take a given course. Equivalent preparation is generally sufficient. If there is doubt about a student’s preparation level, permission to enroll may be requested from the instructor of the course or from the department chairperson. Academic departments reserve the right to deny admission in a course if the prerequisite has not been completed. Academic departments reserve the right to give permission or waive the prerequisite for any course or to substitute for the prerequisite learning obtained by other means than through the prerequisite course(s). See the Courses of Instruction section for each undergraduate college in this bulletin for official listing of course prerequisites.

The use of the words “parallel”, “corequisite”, or “coregister with” in the prerequisite for a course means that both courses are to be taken simultaneously.

Grading System

The University uses an A through F grading system. The letter grades with point value (in parentheses) are: A+ (4.0), A (4.0), A- (3.67), B+ (3.33), B (3.0), B- (2.67), C+ (2.33), C (2.0), C- (1.67), D+ (1.33), D (1.0), D- (0.67), and F (0). Grades of W (dropped/withdrew), I (incomplete), P (pass/C or better), and N (no pass) may also be given. W, I, P, and N are not assigned grade points and therefore are not used in computation of a student’s grade point average.

Academic Standards-Institutional Policy

Probation. A student who receives a semester grade point average (GPA) of less than 2.00 or ends a semester with a cumulative GPA below 2.00 will be placed (or will continue) on probation. The student will remain on probation until a semester is completed with both a semester and cumulative GPA at or above 2.00, or until the student is dismissed.

Academic Dismissal. A student will be dismissed from UNL at the end of any semester* in which the following conditions exist:

1. Cumulative Credit Hours** 1-18: more than one semester attended and a cumulative grade point average (GPA) below 1.00.

2. Cumulative Credit Hours 19-45: cumulative GPA below 2.00 at end of prior semester, and both semester and cumulative GPAs are below 1.75 or three consecutive semesters on probation. The unsuccessful semester which places the student on probation is considered the first of the three consecutive semesters on probation.

3. Cumulative Credit Hours 46 and above: cumulative GPA below 2.00 at end of prior semester, and both semester and cumulative GPAs are below 2.00 or three consecutive semesters on probation.

* NOTE: Course work taken during any of the four summer sessions will be collectively considered as one semester of attendance.

** NOTE: For the purposes of enforcing academic standards, cumulative credit hours include the following:

1. Credit hours that a student registered for and did not drop during the first two weeks of the course. These are the courses that are subject to a grade.

2. All transfer hours presented.

Readmission. A student who has been dismissed from UNL will be denied enrollment privileges for at least two consecutive semesters (the four summer sessions count as one semester) and will not be allowed to enroll until all admission deficiencies have been cleared. Readmission to UNL is not automatic. A dismissed student may apply for readmission to UNL for the semester following the mandatory “stop-out” period or any subsequent semesters. Applications for readmission will be evaluated by the Office of Admissions in accordance with criteria established by each of the colleges. Decisions regarding specific college readmission will be made by the individual college in which the student seeks to enroll after readmission.

Please see college information for specific standards related to the college.

Honors Convocation Recognition Requirements

Honors Convocation recognition requirements for students entering the University after the Spring Semester 2004 require that those eligible for recognition be in the top ten percent of their college class based on their cumulative grade point average (but with a cumulative GPA no lower than 3.6) and meet the additional requirements stated below.

Students whose first college matriculation at UNL (after high school graduation) occurred before June 2004 will be recognized on the basis of recognition requirements in force at that time. This policy will also apply to transfer students from UNO and UNK whose first college matriculation at those institutions preceded the June 2004 implementation of the recognition criteria.

Honors Convocation criteria for students entering the University in the 2004-05 academic year and after are listed below. Students will be recognized only for the highest award for which they qualify.

High Scholarship. Students must be in the top ten percent of their college class based on their cumulative grade point average and meet the following specific requirements:

1. Required semesters in residence at UNL: juniors and seniors must have completed at least 3 semesters or 42 credit hours at UNL; sophomores must have completed at least 2 semesters or 28 credit hours; freshmen must have completed at least 1 semester or 12 credit hours.

2. Hours completed first semester: seniors must complete a minimum of 9 hours, of which 6 must be graded A through F. (Student teachers in the College of Education and Human Sciences may be exceptions.) Students graduating in December may take only those hours needed for graduation. Juniors, sophomores, and freshmen must complete a minimum of 12 hours first (fall) semester, at least 9 of which are graded A through F.

Superior Scholarship. Superior scholarship students are seniors graduating between December and August who: 1) meet the requirements for high scholarship for seniors, and 2) are in the upper three percent of the senior class of their college or have been on the UNL Honors Convocation list each year since matriculation as a freshman.

Chancellor’s Scholars. Seniors graduating between December and August qualify for this award if they meet the following criteria.

1. Graduating seniors must have earned the grade of A in all graded collegiate work at UNL and at other institutions and a grade of P for all classes taken in the Pass/No Pass grading option (excluding foreign study and collegiate work taken prior to the student’s graduation from high school. The student must request the exclusion of a grade taken prior to graduation from high school and the re-calculation of the GPA in writing to the University Honors Program, 118 NRC, 0659, by March 1). At least 42 graded semester hours must have been earned at UNL by the end of first (fall) semester of the academic year of graduation.

2. During first semester, a student must complete a minimum of 9 total hours with no more than 3 hours of Pass/No Pass course work. (Student teachers in the College of Education and Human Sciences may be exceptions.) Students graduating in December may take only those hours needed for graduation.

General Information for Honors. Students with grade changes or students finishing incompletes after January 1 should contact the Office of the University Honors Program to see that these changes have been recorded.

All grades are averaged in figuring cumulative GPA. Students repeating a class to remove C-, D, or F grades will have both the original and the repeat grade used to calculate GPA.

Only those seniors recognized as Superior Scholars and Chancellor’s Scholars (see above) need to order caps and gowns for the Honors Convocation ceremonies. The Honors Convocation invitation will give appropriate instructions.

NOTE: Only University of Nebraska system grades are used to compute the GPA for Honors. For computing the GPA for Honors, a student may request the exclusion of a University of Nebraska system grade earned in a course taken prior to graduation from high school. This request for a re-calculation of the GPA must be made in writing to the University Honors Program, 118 NRC, 0659, prior to March 1. UNL, UNO, UNK, and UNMC students are considered resident students.

NOTE: Each college also has their own recognition.

Recognition of Outstanding Academic Achievement

In addition to providing qualified students with an opportunity to enrich their academic programs by taking honors courses, the University and its colleges recognize the academic achievements of all their talented and dedicated students.

The Honors Convocation: University and Chancellor’s Scholars

In April of each year, the Chancellor hosts the All-University Honors Convocation at which students who meet recognition requirements are honored as University Scholars. Special recognition is given to Chancellor’s Scholars, graduating seniors who have maintained a perfect 4.0 grade point in all their collegiate work.

The Dean’s List: College Scholars

Each semester, the eight undergraduate colleges identify students who perform at a superior level academically by recording their names on the Dean’s List of the respective colleges. These College Scholars have earned at least a B+ average in a specified number of courses (the standard varies from college to college) during the semester for which they are recognized.

Graduation with Distinction in UNL’s Undergraduate Colleges

The colleges also praise their most successful students by recommending them for graduation with distinction, high distinction or highest distinction. While the manner of selection varies from college to college, all graduates with a level of distinction upon graduation have earned the respect of both the university community and the larger society they are about to join. Acknowledgment of such achievement is made publicly at commencement and, of course, is indicated on the student’s diploma.

For further information about Nebraska Honors at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln contact:

Dr. Patrice Berger, Director

University Honors Program

University of Nebraska–Lincoln

118 NRC

PO Box 880659

Lincoln, NE 68588-0659

(402) 472-5425

Departmental Honors

Many academic departments offer honors courses and provide high-ability students with special research opportunities. Students who do not participate in the University Honors Program may request permission to register for an honors course from the course instructor or the department office. Refer to college and departmental listings in this bulletin for further information or contact the University Honors Program Office.

Grading Policies

University faculty members are expected to inform students early in the semester of course objectives, requirements, standards, and grading procedures for the particular course. In addition, they should make clear their individual policies regarding the Pass/No Pass grading option and the assignment of I (incomplete) grades. Failure of any faculty member to inform students of special restrictions in these areas could be grounds for a grade appeal case. Grade appeal procedures exist in all UNL undergraduate colleges (see Grade Appeals in individual undergraduate college sections of this bulletin).

Pass/No Pass Grading Option

The Pass/No Pass grading option was designed to enable students to take courses in areas of interest where they may feel they have had minimal preparation without adversely affecting their grade point average. Grades of P (pass) are interpreted as a grade of C or better. Neither grade P or N (no pass) contributes to the grade point average.

There are collegiate restrictions on the use of this grading option. Students should see Pass/No Pass in individual undergraduate college sections of this bulletin, see the Schedule of Classes, and talk with their academic advisers concerning the use of this option.

Grades of Incomplete

The grade I is used by an instructor at the end of a term to designate incomplete work in a course. It should be used only when students are unable to complete the requirements of the course in the term in which they are registered because of illness, military service, hardship, or death in the immediate family. Incompletes should only be given if the student has already substantially completed the major requirements of the course.

For complete procedures and regulations, see the Schedule of Classes and the Summer Sessions Bulletin.

Course Repeat Policy

Only the most recent letter grade received in a given course will be used in computing a student’s cumulative grade point average if the student has completed the course more than once and previously received a grade or grades below C in that course.

The previous grade (or grades) will not be used in computation of the cumulative grade point average, but it will remain a part of the academic record and will appear on any transcript.

A student can remove from his/her cumulative average a course grade of C-, D+, D, D-, or F if the student repeats the equivalent course at the University of Nebraska and receives a grade other than P (pass), I (incomplete), N (no pass), W (withdrew), or NR (no report). If a course is no longer being offered, it is not eligible for the removal process.

For complete procedures and regulations, see the Schedule of Classes and the Summer Sessions Bulletin.

Automatic Removal of Grade Factors From Cumulative GPA For Repeated Courses

Courses graded A+ to F for the current semester are checked against all courses taken since the installation of the computerized records system (September, 1986) and grade factors are automatically subtracted for repeated courses originally graded C-, D+, D, D-, or F.

Exceptions to Automatic Grade Factor Removal Processing

Independent study courses, special topics courses and variable credit hour courses will not be processed automatically. These courses will be identified to Registration and Records to check the C-, D+, D, D- or F status manually. Any of these courses that qualify for removal will be processed manually by Registration and Records. The student will be notified of the change by a Grade Notification letter.

Students must complete an “Undergraduate Course Repeat Re-Computation Request” for the following situations:

1. Repeated courses which were first taken prior to the First Semester 1986-87.

2. UNMC, UNO, UNK equivalent course.

3. Late grades or grade changes after the grade census date (approximately three weeks after the end of the term).

4. Cross-listed courses (i.e., FINA 365/ECON 365).

Requests for course repeat(s) processing for these exception-type situations are available at, and must be submitted to Registration and Records, 107 Canfield Administration Building, approximately three weeks after the end of the term. Removals processed during this revision period will be reflected in the official (census date) cumulative grade point average. Students not meeting this deadline will be notified of the change approximately two weeks after the request is received. Late changes will not be reflected in the official (census date) cumulative grade point average.

Academic Bankruptcy

A student may remove one or two complete semesters of work from their cumulative grade point average and degree consideration by applying to Registration and Records for academic bankruptcy. To qualify, a student must have completed either 15 simultaneous or sequential credit hours with a minimum 3.0 grade point average or 30 hours with a minimum 2.5 grade point average at UNL following the semester(s) the student wishes to remove.

In order to declare a semester bankrupt, all courses taken during the semester are bankrupt (both credit hours and grades). The bankrupt semester is removed from consideration for cumulative grade point average purposes and the bankrupt credit is not used for degree requirements. The semester listing of courses and grades remain evident on the academic record which is used to issue transcripts. A student may not bankrupt a semester after receiving a baccalaureate degree. College Independent Study via Extended Education and Outreach is not included in computing qualifying grade point averages; P grades may not be used to meet bankruptcy requirements.

For complete procedures and regulations, see the Schedule of Classes.

Advanced Placement

In order to help students gain credit by advanced standing, the University provides opportunities for advanced placement. UNL participates in the Advanced Placement Program (AP) of the College Entrance Examination Board and the College Level Examination Program (CLEP). Students can obtain detailed information on acceptable courses from the Office of Admissions.

Credit by Examination

Some currently-enrolled students, through outside study or relevant experience, may feel prepared to demonstrate that they have attained the knowledge and/or skills required to pass a particular UNL course. As an alternative to enrolling in the course, such students may elect to take a proficiency exam which tests for mastery of the course material. If a student scores satisfactorily on the examination, the student may be awarded credit for the course. Students can obtain detailed information from the dean’s office of their college.

Graduation Requirements

UNL Policy: Removal of High School Deficiencies (approved by UNL Dean’s Council, August 29, 2006)

UNL students are expected to remove all high school deficiencies within the first 30 hours (foreign language is to be removed within 60 hours) of their course work at UNL. Students will not be permitted to graduate from UNL unless they have met the requirements for removal of a high school deficiency; however, the college Dean has the authority to determine the individual circumstances under which a student has met the intent of completing the high school deficiency and may graduate.

Oversight Responsibility and Notification Process

In May of each academic year the Office of Registration and Records will notify students who have not made progress towards removal from their official UNL records of any high school course deficiency with which they entered a degree program at UNL. The notification will contain the UNL policy as well as a recommendation will be made that the student meet with his/her academic adviser for assistance.

The student’s academic adviser will receive notification through a copy of the student letter to place in student’s advising folder.

The college dean will receive a listing of all students in the college who were notified as well as the number of credit hours completed by the student, the deficiency and the name of the student’s assigned adviser.

General Education Requirements (ACE)

First-year students who begin matriculation at UNL in fall 2009 are required to complete the new general education requirements for the Achievement–Centered Education (ACE) Program.

It is anticipated that UNL students matriculating prior to fall 2009 will continue to complete the CEP General Education Program requirements as designated by the bulletin year in which the student started his or her UNL college program. (See page 389). Students who transfer to UNL as of fall 2009 may elect to complete their program under the CEP General Education Program requirements. See your academic adviser.

Achievement-Centered Education (ACE)

Consistent with the mission and values of the University, ACE is based on a shared set of four institutional objectives and 10 student learning outcomes. The ACE program was approved by faculty in all eight undergraduate colleges and endorsed by the Faculty Senate, the student government, and the Academic Planning Committee in January 2008 for implementation in the fall 2009. ACE aligns with current national initiatives in general education.

Key characteristics of ACE demonstrate the benefits of the program to students:

Students receive a broad education with exposure to multiple disciplines, critical life skills and important reasoning, inquiry, and civic capacities.
ACE is simple and transparent for students, faculty and advisers. Students complete the equivalent of 3 credit hours for each of the ten student learning outcomes.
Students connect and integrate their ACE experiences with their selected major.
Students can transfer all ACE certified courses across colleges within the institution to meet the ACE requirement and any course from outside the institution that is directly equivalent to a UNL ACE-certified course. Courses from outside institutions without direct equivalents may be considered with appropriate documentation for ACE credit (see academic adviser).
ACE allows faculty to assess and improve their effectiveness and facilitate students’ learning.

ACE Institutional Objectives and Student Learning Outcomes

To meet the ACE Program requirement, a student will complete the equivalent of 3 credit hours for each of the following ten ACE Student Learning Outcomes (a total of 30 ACE credit hours):

Institutional Objective 1:

Develop intellectual and practical skills, including proficiency in written, oral, and visual communication; inquiry techniques; critical and creative thinking; quantitative applications; information assessment; teamwork; and problem-solving.

ACE 1: Write texts, in various forms, with an identified purpose, that respond to specific audience needs, incorporate research or existing knowledge, and use applicable documentation and appropriate conventions of format and structure.

ACE 2: Demonstrate communication competence in one or more of the following ways: (a) by making oral presentations with supporting materials, (b) by leading and participating in problem-solving teams, (c) by employing a repertoire of communication skills for developing and maintaining professional and personal relationships, or (d) by creating and interpreting visual information.

ACE 3: Use mathematical, computational, statistical, or formal reasoning (including reasoning based on principles of logic) to solve problems, draw inferences, and determine reasonableness.

Institutional Objective 2:

Build knowledge of diverse peoples and cultures and of the natural and physical world through the study of mathematics, sciences and technologies, histories, humanities, arts, social sciences, and human diversity.

ACE 4: Use scientific methods and knowledge of the natural and physical world to address problems through inquiry, interpretation, analysis, and the making of inferences from data, to determine whether conclusions or solutions are reasonable.

ACE 5: Use knowledge, historical perspectives, analysis, interpretation, critical evaluation, and the standards of evidence appropriate to the humanities to address problems and issues.

ACE 6: Use knowledge, theories, methods, and historical perspectives appropriate to the social sciences to understand and evaluate human behavior.

ACE 7: Use knowledge, theories, or methods appropriate to the arts to understand their context and significance.

Institutional Objective 3:

Exercise individual and social responsibilities through the study of ethical principles and reasoning, application of civic knowledge, interaction with diverse cultures, and engagement with global issues.

ACE 8: Explain ethical principles, civics, and stewardship, and their importance to society.

ACE 9: Exhibit global awareness or knowledge of human diversity through analysis of an issue.

Institutional Objective 4:

Integrate these abilities and capacities, adapting them to new settings, questions, and responsibilities.

ACE 10: Generate a creative or scholarly product that requires broad knowledge, appropriate technical proficiency, information collection, synthesis, interpretation, presentation, and reflection.

ACE Structural Criteria

Graduates of the University of Nebraska–Lincoln will satisfy the requirements of their majors, their colleges, and the ACE Program.

1. ACE courses are credit-bearing curricular offerings or equivalent documented co-curricular experiences.

2. The ACE Program will consist of the equivalent of 3 credit hours for each of the ten ACE Student Learning Outcomes.

3. Any ACE course approved to satisfy an ACE Student Learning Outcome satisfies that Student Learning Outcome in all UNL undergraduate colleges.

4. Up to three ACE Student Learning Outcomes 4-10 may be satisfied by work in one subject area.

5. ACE Student Learning Outcomes must be satisfied by work in at least three subject areas.

6. No ACE course may satisfy more than one ACE Student Learning Outcome in a student’s program.

7. If an ACE course addressed two ACE Student Learning Outcomes, the student decides which one of the two Outcomes the course will satisfy in that student’s program.

8. Every ACE course will reinforce at least one of the following as appropriate for the discipline and as identified by the department offering the course: Writing, Oral Communication, Visual Literacy, Historical Perspectives, Mathematics and Statistics, Critical Thinking, Teamwork, Problem Solving, Ethics, Civics, Social Responsibility, Global Awareness, or Human Diversity.

ACE courses are identified in course descriptions by the ACE symbol followed by the Student Learning Outcome number(s) that they fulfill. See the ACE Web site at: http://ace.unl.edu for the most current information and the most recently certified courses.

Special Undergraduate Programs

Preprofessional Studies

In addition to undergraduate programs leading to a bachelors degree, several UNL colleges offer preprofessional programs of study designed to prepare students for advanced training or professional study after graduation.

These are not programs with a predetermined outline of courses leading to a degree in a specific professional field. Rather, with careful planning and an adviser’s assistance, students build a degree program designed to enhance knowledge in areas relevant to future professional work.

Students can obtain advising and courses for preprofessional studies from three undergraduate colleges at the University. The College of Agricultural Sciences and Natural Resources offers preforestry and preveterinary medicine; the College of Architecture offers prearchitecture and preinterior design; the College of Arts and Sciences offers preparation in prechiropractic, preclinical perfusion science, precytotechnology, predental hygiene, predentistry, prelaw, premedical technology, premedicine, premortuary science, prenuclear medicine technology, preoccupational therapy, preoptometry, prepharmacy, prephysical therapy, prephysician’s assistant, preradiologic technology, and preseminary/theology information.

Students can develop a prelaw program in any of UNL’s undergraduate colleges, but they should choose their courses carefully beginning their freshman year.

The University Honors Program

The University Honors Program is a special program for which formal application is required. Students admitted to the Program have ACT composite scores in the upper 20s or above, are in the top ten percent of their high school class and, most importantly, have demonstrated a commitment to intellectual curiosity and academic excellence. Acceptance into the Program is based on a comprehensive evaluation of the student’s potential by the Honors Program Faculty Committee. All the undergraduate colleges support the Program, and honors courses apply to college and major requirements. A special notation is made on the transcript and diploma upon graduation from the University Honors Program to inform graduate schools and employers of the student’s superior performance. Honors Program students may request housing in the honors residence, the Neihardt Residence Center.

Students admitted to the Honors Program in their first year of college must fulfill the following requirements in order to complete the Program:

A. Full-time student: 12 credit hours each semester (fall and spring)

B. Cumulative GPA: 3.5

C. 24 credit hours in honors courses with a grade of B or better: to include 189H and 395H

D. Sequence:

First and Second years:

Complete 15 honors credit hours with a grade of B or better in the first four semesters of college work including 189H and file a Statement of Academic Interest.

Complete at least 6 honors credit hours with a grade of B or better each year (Fall and/or Spring).

Third and Fourth years:

Complete 9 honors credit hours with a grade of B or better in the junior and senior years, including 395H.

File a Memorandum of Study (research prospectus) prior to completing 100 hours.

Complete at least 3 honors credit hours with a grade of B or better each year (Fall or Spring)

E. Completion of an honors research or creative project (e.g., thesis).

Students admitted to the Program having earned college credits after high school graduation either at the University of Nebraska or another school should discuss modified requirements with the Honors Program director.

Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management

The Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Managementt develops leaders for a technology-driven world. Graduates will be professionals who understand the multiple levels of new information systems, and who become the technology sector’s innovators, product developers, entrepreneurs, chief information officers, and CEOs.

The undergraduate program is designed to give students a strong well-rounded education and to give them not only the ability to create information technology applications and solutions, but also the capacity to understand the implications of information technology for business and society. The program produces graduates with high technical proficiency as well as a strong sense of the business problems and organizational needs that information systems are intended to serve.

Students interested in learning more about the Jeffrey S. Raikes School of Computer Science and Management are encouraged to call the Program at 472-6000 or visit the Program Web site at raikes.unl.edu.

International Affairs

The Office of International Affairs (IA) is a service organization, reporting to the Senior Vice Chancellor for Academic Affairs. IA’s mission is to support students, faculty, and administrators in all academic units as these engage in international education. Through partnerships and collaborative projects, we assist faculty, administrators, students, and staff to position UNL as a leading global campus and to enhance its visibility around the world.

International Affairs prepares students for work, citizenship, and life in a complex and fast-changing world through experiences that integrate new ideas and cultural perspectives. The work in the office engages communities on campus and around the state and contributes directly to creating a culture at the University that values diversity of ideas and people. International Affairs provides service to all Nebraska schools, business, and communities. It represents the University of Nebraska–Lincoln in multi-institutional associations, national and international organizations and agencies, and bi-national and multi-national projects related to teaching, research, and public service.

International Affairs assists more than 700 students each year to engage in academic experiences abroad for a semester, academic year, or summer session. The Office sponsors the Fulbright Program for students and faculty and assists faculty in the preparation of grants and contracts that involve study abroad and international cooperation. Staff members provide advice to exchange students from partner institutions overseas’ they advise and assist students who return from study abroad via orientations for re-entry and cultural programming, offering all students the opportunity to develop skills in intercultural communication when they return to UNL. They also coordinate short-term courses offered by UNL faculty in foreign countries during the Winterim (winter break), spring break, and through the UNL World Campus over the summer. For more information, see “Study Abroad and Exchange Programs” on page 20 of this bulletin.

International Affairs provides immigration, personal, and cross-cultural advising to more than 1700 international students and scholars and their dependents from more than 100 countries. Staff members counsel international students and scholars abou their new educational and cultural environment, advise them about immigration regulations, and provide activities to enhance their academic experiences at the University and integrate them into the local community. They also serve as intercultural resources for UNL faculty and staff who interact with international students and scholars. For more information, see “International Student and Scholar Services” on page 25 of this bulletin.

The Office coordinates international agreements that link UNL with other institutions of higher education around the world. International Affairs helps to negotiate and draft such agreements and memoranda of understanding and serves as the repository for the signed documents. IA serves all campus units re hiring of foreign faculty, researchers and professional staff and helps faculty members to network with other who may have academic interest or collaborations with the same institutions or in the same country. IA acts as an advocate for academic projects that promote international education, such as The Global Classroom, which links students, face to face in real time, with students from other countries. The Office also sponsors conferences with international themes, brings distinguished international speakers to campus and serves as host for many international visitors.

The Library and resource center at International Affairs offers faculty, students, and staff, information about working, traveling, or performing voluntary service in another country. The Office also provides travel services to students and staff who go abroad.-ADD LINK TO IA

Study Abroad and Exchange Programs

International Affairs offers a wide variety of overseas study opportunities to UNL undergraduate and graduate students for a semester, academic year, semester break, or summer period. With careful planning, credit earned during study abroad can be used toward degree requirements. Most programs can be arranged to complement regular degree programs. Credit earned on UNL and UNL-approved programs is considered resident credit for degree requirement purposes. In all cases, students register at UNL which means that most existing scholarships and financial aid remain in effect. A limited number of partial scholarships, reserved for participation in study abroad programs, are available. The cost of study for many programs is similar to regular tuition, room and board costs at UNL. More than 700 UNL students participate in study abroad each year. –INSERT LINK TO STUDY ABROAD

ROTC Program

Students at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln have the opportunity to combine their academic studies with training to become an officer in Army, Navy, Marine Corps, or Air Force through the Reserve Officers Training Corps. For further information, see “Reserve Officers Training Corps” –ADD LINK

Summer Sessions

UNL’s Summer Sessions is a great way to begin, continue, or advance one’s education through more than 1,400 courses offered by 70 departments. It provides options and flexibility by offering courses in a three-week pre-session, an eight week session, and two five-week sessions.

During the summer, a wide range of students will be on campus—current UNL students, new first-year students, transfer students, visiting students, and high school students. Students take summer courses to meet entrance requirements, to shorten the time to graduation, to lighten the course load required in other terms, to concentrate on areas of study that need full-time attention, and to overcome academic deficiencies.

Although Summer Sessions maintains the same high standards of quality education as the regular academic year, it does tend to be less formal, with smaller classes and more accessible instructors. For information about course offerings or enrolling during Summer Sessions contact:

Summer Sessions Office

University of Nebraska–Lincoln

208 Canfield Administration Building

PO Box 880421

Lincoln, NE 68588-0421

(402) 472-3567

(800) 562-1035 (toll-free)

summer.unl.edu

Extended Education & Outreach

Extended Education and Outreach assists academic units in offering a variety of courses and degree programs that can be taken at any time and/or any place. Courses are offered in one or a combination of formats including online, video, print, audio, e-mail and the traditional classroom setting. This flexibility in format and scheduling offers students the convenience of taking courses at a time and place that fits their needs. –ADD LINK

Libraries

The University’s library system and services are extensive, including more than 3,170,000 volumes and 28,000 active periodicals and serials. In addition to needed library resources, UNL’s libraries provide group study spaces, multi-media equipment and snack areas.

The University Libraries and the Marvin and Virginia Schmid Law Library offer both in-house and remote access to a wide variety of electronic resources. The Libraries Web site, http://iris.unl.edu, currently includes the Libraries electronic catalog, general and specialized journal indexes, full-text electronic journals, image databases, and a host of Internet resources. Many library services such as reference and research assistance are offered electronically to supplement traditional services.

Love Memorial Library, the largest library facility on campus, holds 1,600,000 volumes.

The library system also operates more specialized facilities on both UNL campuses. On City Campus, these include the architecture, engineering, geology, mathematics, and music libraries. The Schmid Law Library is located on the University’s East Campus. C.Y. Thompson Library, also on the East Campus, is the largest branch library in the UNL system. Its collection emphasizes materials related to agriculture, home economics, and dentistry.

Graduate Studies

The University of Nebraska–Lincoln has a rich tradition of graduate education dating back to the later nineteenth century. The University takes great pride in belonging to the prestigious Association of American Universities as a founding member and as being recognized as a Carnegie Comprehensive Doctoral (no med/vet) Institution. For more than a century, scholar-teachers at UNL have stood on the cutting edge in advancing the knowledge of their respective fields. The presence of graduate programs and the research they foster by graduate professors and students greatly enriches undergraduate education at UNL.

Students intending to continue their education after graduating from UNL may take advantage of graduate studies programs that allow seniors to take and receive credit for graduate courses prior to receiving their bachelors degrees. Training graduate students who have the highest possible degree of professional competence combined with a strong sense of social responsibility continues to be a principal goal of UNL.

Admission of UNL Seniors

Seniors at UNL needing not more than 9 undergraduate credit hours to complete the bachelors degree and wishing to register for graduate credit may be granted admission to a Graduate College degree program on a provisional basis subject to receiving their baccalaureates within one calendar year. They must file an application for admission to Graduate Studies and, if admitted, their registration may count as residence in the Graduate College.

Graduate Courses Taken by UNL Seniors

UNL seniors who have obtained in advance the approval of the Dean of Graduate Studies may enroll in up to 12 hours credit for graduate courses taken in addition to the courses necessary to complete their undergraduate work, provided that such credits are earned within the calendar year prior to receipt of the baccalaureate.

Course work taken prior to receipt of the baccalaureate may not always be accepted for transfer to other institutions as graduate work.

Seniors in the University Honors Program are encouraged to consider taking 400/800-level courses at the 800 level with the concurrence of their adviser and permission of the instructor and Dean of Graduate Studies.

Please contact the Office of Graduate Studies, 1100 Seaton Hall, prior to registering for graduate course work. Completion of a Hold for Graduate Credit Form is required.

###